<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Logistics on CMSC423: Bioinformatic Algorithms Databases and Tools (Spring 2017)</title>
    <link>http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/logistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Logistics on CMSC423: Bioinformatic Algorithms Databases and Tools (Spring 2017)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 05:41:03 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/logistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Logistics</title>
      <link>http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/logistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 05:41:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/logistics/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This page constitutes the official syllabus for this class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-information&#34;&gt;Course Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bioinformatic tools, algorithms and databases&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;CMSC423 Spring 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lecture Meeting Times&lt;br /&gt;
Tuesday and Thursday, 9:30pm-10:45pm, CSI 1122&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instructor:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cbcb.umd.edu/~hcorrada&#34;&gt;H&amp;eacute;ctor Corrada Bravo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Center for Bioinformatics and Computational Biology&lt;br /&gt;
Department of Computer Science&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:hcorrada@umiacs.umd.edu&#34;&gt;hcorrada@umiacs.umd.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Office: 3114F Biomolecular Sciences Building&lt;br /&gt;
Phone Number: 301-405-2481&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Office Hours:&lt;/strong&gt; Friday 1:00pm-2:00pm AVW 3223 and by appointment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communication:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For course related questions, use &lt;a href=&#34;https://piazza.com/class/iybyz4l8fqs2bl
&#34;&gt;Piazza&lt;/a&gt; as indicated below.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For any other communication (e.g., absences accomodations etc.) email me including &lt;code&gt;[CMSC320]&lt;/code&gt; in the message subject.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;TA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aya Ismail
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:asalam@umd.edu&#34;&gt;asalam@umd.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Office Hours: TBD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will use the class Piazza site &lt;a href=&#34;https://piazza.com/class/iybyz4l8fqs2bl
&#34;&gt;https://piazza.com/class/iybyz4l8fqs2bl
&lt;/a&gt; for questions, discussion and announcements. Assignments and grades for the class will be posted to the class ELMS site: &lt;a href=&#34;https://myelms.umd.edu/courses/1218381
&#34;&gt;https://myelms.umd.edu/courses/1218381
&lt;/a&gt;.
In case of an extended emergency closure, announcements on policy and procedures will be posted to Piazza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;textbook-and-resources&#34;&gt;Textbook and Resources:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be using &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformaticsalgorithms.com/
&#34;&gt;Compeau, P. and Pevsner, P., Bioinformatics Algorithms, An Active Learning Approach, 2nd. edition, Vols. 1 and 2. Active Learning Publishers, La Jolla, CA, 2015.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This text book is accompanied by a set of video lectures that you can view in preparation for class discussion during class meeting times. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/bioinfalgorithms/playlists
&#34;&gt;Video playlists are available on youtube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class meeting times will (for the most part) not be lecture time&lt;/strong&gt;. The goal is to use class time to explore Biological and Algorithmic aspects of materials in depth and collaboratively with your peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming exercises and problems are integrated with the
    textbook readings and videos. We will use the
    &lt;a href=&#34;http://rosalind.info&#34;&gt;Rosalind Project&lt;/a&gt; to manage programming
    exercises and submissions. More information below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;expected-outcomes-and-topics-covered&#34;&gt;Expected outcomes and topics covered&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this course, students will be able to describe,
implement and analyze algorithms that solve fundamental problems in
biological sequence analysis: sequence alignment and assembly, string
querying, sequence signal finding, and data clustering. They will also be able to identify and use appropriate publicly available resources, both data and tools, to perform common bioinformatics tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;expectations-for-students&#34;&gt;Expectations for Students&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;class-prep&#34;&gt;Class prep&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/
/calendar/index.html&#34;&gt;Course Calendar&lt;/a&gt; will list
readings (usually from &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioinformaticsalgorithms.com/
&#34;&gt;the textbook&lt;/a&gt;, on
occassion uploaded to &lt;a href=&#34;https://myelms.umd.edu/courses/1218381
&#34;&gt;ELMS&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;strong&gt;You are
required to read this material before lecture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/
/calendar/index.html&#34;&gt;Course Calendar&lt;/a&gt; will also
list programming exercises to &lt;strong&gt;attempt&lt;/strong&gt; before lecture. You
will upload attempted solutions to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rosalind.info/classes/400/
&#34;&gt;pre-lecture exercise
Rosalind page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/
/calendar/index.html&#34;&gt;Course Calendar&lt;/a&gt; will list
any quizzes or written assignments to be completed before lecture. You
must submit these assignments &lt;strong&gt;before lecture&lt;/strong&gt; as instructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;programming-projects&#34;&gt;Programming projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming exercises on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rosalind.info/classes/401/
&#34;&gt;final submission
Rosalind page&lt;/a&gt; will be collected into
&lt;em&gt;programming projects&lt;/em&gt;. Some additional analysis using the programs
you write for these exercises will be assigned. Those additional
analysis will be submitted as instructed. Full descriptions of the
programming projects will be posted in the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/
/index/projects.html&#34;&gt;Programming Projects course
page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;written-assignments&#34;&gt;Written assignments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some written exercises will be assigned covering material we
have discussed in class. Some of these will be posted on the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hcbravo.org/cmsc423/
/calendar/index.html&#34;&gt;Course Calendar&lt;/a&gt; and announced on
the class &lt;a href=&#34;https://piazza.com/class/iybyz4l8fqs2bl
&#34;&gt;Piazza page&lt;/a&gt;. Other in-class exercises
may not be announced ahead of time. See below
for class policies on attendance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;announcements-and-discussion&#34;&gt;Announcements and discussion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://piazza.com/class/iybyz4l8fqs2bl
&#34;&gt;Piazza page&lt;/a&gt; for class
announcements. Please use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://piazza.com/class/iybyz4l8fqs2bl
&#34;&gt;Piazza page&lt;/a&gt; for
class discussion. Note that the Rosalind Project class pages also have
discussion capability. &lt;strong&gt;Do not use it&lt;/strong&gt;, please use the
&lt;a href=&#34;{{ site.piazza_url }}&#34;&gt;Piazza page&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;em&gt;all discussion&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;participation-grade&#34;&gt;Participation grade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;syllabus.html&#34;&gt;course grading scheme&lt;/a&gt; includes a class participation grade. You can earn full credit for this in three ways: (1) lecture participation, asking questions and answering your peers questions, (2) piazza participation, asking and answering questions on piazza, (3) regular attendance to office hours. To earn full credit you should aim to ask or answer a question at least once every two weeks on lecture or on piazza; or attend office hours at least once a month (that can include just going to my office hours to chat about computer science, biology, science, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-policies&#34;&gt;Other policies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be reading assignments. Students are expected to have read the material &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; class.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students are expected to attend lectures. Active participation is expected. There will be graded work done in class.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assignments are to be handed-in electronically or in class as instructed on their due date. Late assignments will not be accepted.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be graded work to be done in class. Students not in class that day, except for an excused absence, will not be able to complete that work outside class.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students may discuss homeworks and projects in groups. However, each
student must write and/or program solutions independently.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Posting project solutions in a public online location without
express consent and permission from the instructor is a violation of
academic integrity policy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cell phone usage is &lt;strong&gt;prohibited&lt;/strong&gt; during lecture, laptop use will be allowed to the extent that students &lt;strong&gt;demonstrably&lt;/strong&gt; use it to follow along an in-class analysis or demonstration.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;grading-procedures&#34;&gt;Grading Procedures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lecture prep work (15%): to be done before class, includes programming exercises and short written assignments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Written homework (15%): some will be take-home, some will be done in class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming projects (25%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Midterms (2) (20%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Final (20%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Class participation (5%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;university-policies-and-resources&#34;&gt;University Policies and Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policies relevant to Undergraduate Courses are found here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ugst.umd.edu/courserelatedpolicies.html&#34;&gt;http://ugst.umd.edu/courserelatedpolicies.html&lt;/a&gt;. Topics that are addressed in these various policies include academic integrity, student and instructor conduct, accessibility and accommodations, attendance and excused absences, grades and appeals, copyright and intellectual property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-evaluations&#34;&gt;Course evaluations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course evaluations are important and that the department and faculty
take student feedback seriously.  Students can go to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.courseevalum.umd.edu&#34;&gt;http://www.courseevalum.umd.edu&lt;/a&gt; to complete their evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>