<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homeworks on CMSC828O: Networks Across Scales (Fall 2019)</title>
    <link>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homeworks on CMSC828O: Networks Across Scales (Fall 2019)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Released under the MIT license</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Homework: Network Structure Inference</title>
      <link>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/net_structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/net_structure/</guid>
      <description>Posted: 11/6/2018
Last Update: 11/6/2018
Data Download timeseries data derived from the ADHD-200 resting fMRI samples (http://fcon_1000.projects.nitrc.org/indi/adhd200/).
https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/ data/roi_timeseries.csv.
The data consists of standardized measurements over 176 time points of 39 regions of interest (ROI). The rows of the data correspond to the 39 regions, the first column contains a label indicating the name of the brain ROI, with the remaining columns corresponding to the fMRI timeseries.
Correlation Network Build a correlation network from the timeseries data as follows:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homework: Statistical Analysis of Network Data</title>
      <link>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/stat_models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/stat_models/</guid>
      <description>DUE: Monday 11/4/2019, 11:59pm
Posted: 10/21/2019
Last Update: 10/21/2019
We will use ecological network data from the paper &amp;ldquo;How Structured is the Entangled Bank?&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; by Kefi et al. http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1002527. This paper used Stochastic Block Models to analyze both trophic and non-trophic species interaction networks. Your goal in this homework is to (a) partially replicate some of the analyses in the paper, and reanalyze this data using other statistical methods for analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homework: Network Models</title>
      <link>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/network_models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/network_models/</guid>
      <description>DUE: Wednesday 10/2/2019, 11:59pm
Posted: 9/16/2019
Last Update: 9/30/2019
In our previous homework you generated the degree distribution of a genetic interaction network:
Note: you can obtain a csv file with the adjacency matrix for the genetic interaction dataset here: https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/ data/genetic_interaction.csv.gz.
Question 1: Is this degree distribution consistent with a network generated by the Erdös-Renyi network model? Why?
Fitting the degree distribution Use a network analysis library to estimate the degree exponent under a power-law model for the genetic interaction network.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homework: Practice with Network Statistics</title>
      <link>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/network_stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/network_stats/</guid>
      <description>DUE: Friday 9/13/2017, 11:59pm
Posted: 9/1/2017
Last Update: 9/9/2017
Data Obtain data for the year genetic interaction network at http://thecellmap.org/costanzo2016/. Download data in matrix format from http://thecellmap.org/costanzo2016/data_files/Raw%20genetic%20interaction%20datasets:%20Matrix%20format.zip, and after unzipping use file Data File S2. Raw genetic interaction datasets: Matrix format/SGA_NxN_clustered.cdt This is a tab-separated value file with the following format:
 The first five rows contain metadata. Rows six to the end contain interaction data The first six columns also contain metadata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up R</title>
      <link>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/rocker/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 00:05:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.hcbravo.org/networks-across-scales/homeworks/rocker/</guid>
      <description>For class we will be using R, Rstudio and git. You can download and install each using the links below. However, you can instead use Rocker, a project built on top of Docker to manage your software installation. We&amp;rsquo;ve setup a container that will provide you with a working installation of R, and the Rstudio IDE, along with a lot of packages providing analysis tools and datasets we will use throughout the semester.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>